Guide to the Owen Luck, Photographs of Haida Gwaii, British Columbia
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Photographs of Haida Gwaii, British Columbia
2012-2012
WA Photos Folio 178
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5
3 boxes
Photographs of Haida Gwaii (formerly known as the Queen Charlotte Islands), British Columbia, created during the summer of 2012, and printed as 77 inkjet prints that document the Haida and Kwakwak'awakw (also known as Kwakiutl) people and cultures.
Luck, Owen Craig, 1947-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Owen Luck on the Walter McClintock Memorial Fund, 2013.
Arrangement
Arranged by the photographer.
Owen Luck (born 1947)
Owen Luck is an American photographer known for his photography of Native American and First Nation Canadian life and history. In 1973, after serving two tours as a combat medic in Vietnam, Luck travelled to Pine Ridge, South Dakota to provide medical support during the occupation of Wounded Knee by the American Indian Movement (AIM). He also carried a camera and created an extensive record of the confrontation between AIM and the United States Marshals Service, Federal Bureau of Investigation agents, and other law enforcement agencies. His account of that experience, "A Witness at Wounded Knee 1973," was published in The Princeton University Library Chronicle in 2006. In 1975 Luck documented the Menominee Warrior Society's occupation of the abandoned Alexian Brothers Novitiate in Gresham, Wisconsin, near the Menominee Indian Reservation. Since 2004 he has worked among indigenous communities of the Pacific Northwest. Luck has donated photographs to Ogallala Lakota College in Pine Ridge, to the Haida Gwaii Museum in Skidegate, and to the Makah Museum in Neah Bay. Significant collections of his work are held by Princeton University Library and the Beinecke Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Description of Papers
Photographs of Haida Gwaii (formerly known as the Queen Charlotte Islands), British Columbia, created during the summer of 2012, that document the Haida and Kwakwak'awakw (also known as Kwakiutl) people and cultures.
Images of Haida include portraits of Haida artisans Christian White and Vernon White as well as dancers from the Tluu Xaada Naay Society (Canoe Peoples House) including Roberta Kennedy (Haida name Kung Jaadee), Cynthia Anne Samuels (Haida name Gulee), Tiffany Amber Vanderhoop, and Bryce Williams (member of the Coast Salish). Includes images from the coronation of Allen Davidson (Haida name Skil Hiilans) from the St'langng Laanaas clan as one of the potlatched hereditary leaders of Haida, which was also attended by fellow Haida leader Roy Collison (Haida name Gya awhlans) of the Kuun Laanaas clan. Other images include the burning of a headdress by Georgia Liddle Bennett (Haida name K'inggay 'liwaans).
Images related to the Kwakwak'awakw include views at Alert Bay on Cormorant Island of totem poles, the "big house," and the derelict St. Michael's Indian Residential School. A group of images document a potlatch at the big house in Alert Bay led by Beau Dick (Kwakwak'awakw name Walas Gwa'yam) that includes an initiation ceremony for the Hamatsa society, dances, and the burning of traditional masks with identified attendees including Corey Bullpit, Bill Cranmer, Gwaliga Hart, and Christian White.
The collection also includes a view of the mural, Sunset Whale Tail, by Jeff King at Prince Rupert.
Signed, numbered, and dated by the photographer on versos of prints.
Edition number 1 of 15.
Conditions Governing Access
The Owen Luck, Photographs of Haida Gwaii, British Columbia, are the physical property of the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University. Literary rights, including copyright, belong to the authors or their legal heirs and assigns. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Coast Salish Indians -- Pictorial works; Coast Salish Indians -- Portraits; Haida Indians -- Pictorial works; Haida Indians -- Portraits; Indian masks -- British Columbia -- Pictorial works; Indians of North America -- Pictorial works; Indians of North America -- Portraits; Kwakiutl Indians -- Pictorial works; Kwakiutl Indians -- Portraits; Kwakiutl Indians -- Rites and ceremonies -- Pictorial works; Totem poles -- British Columbia -- Alert Bay; Alert Bay (B.C.) -- Pictorial works; British Columbia -- Pictorial works; Haida Gwaii (B.C.) -- Pictorial works; Prince Rupert (B.C.) -- Pictorial works; Inkjet prints; Photographs; Owen Luck; Bennett, Georgia Liddle -- Portraits; Bullpit, Corey -- Portraits; Cranmer, Bill -- Portraits; Davidson, Allen -- Portraits; Dick, Beau, 1955-2017 -- Portraits; Hart, Gwaliga -- Portraits; Kennedy, Roberta -- Portraits; Samuels, Cynthia Anne -- Portraits; Vanderhoop, Tiffany Amber -- Portraits; White, Christian, 1962- -- Portraits; White, Vernon, 1980- -- Portraits; Williams, Bryce -- Portraits; St. Michael's Indian Residential School (Alert Bay, B.C.) -- Pictorial works
- Inkjet Prints
  Arrangement
  Arranged by the photographer.
  Scope and Contents
  Photographs of Haida Gwaii (formerly known as the Queen Charlotte Islands), British Columbia, created during the summer of 2012, that document the Haida and Kwakwak'awakw (also known as Kwakiutl) people and cultures.
  The descriptive titles of images and associated notes in this guide are by the photographer. Notes by the processing archivist are in brackets.
  - Haida Gwaii
    - 1. Prince Rupert Mural, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 1)
      "I have photographed many times in [black-and-white] but it never resonated as it does in color."
      [The mural is Sunset Whale Tail by Jeff King.]
    - 2. Christian White and his son Vernon, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 2)
      "Christian has since completed the Totem Pole and, as is his wont, [he] has not revealed the final destination of the Pole to be raised. Sharing with only a few of us the story the pole tells. I will disclose the story and the raising site after the task is completed."
    - 3. Christian laying out totem pole, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 4. Christian getting tattoo, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 5. Finished tattoo, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 6. Burning Ravens Tail headdress, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 6)
      "This evening was particularly poignant as Georgia Bennett, [a] Raven's Tail Weaver, passed a Ravens Tail Headdress around the fire to be cut and thrown piece by piece and. burned in the fire.
      A few years ago, a man posing as a photographer came to Haida Gwaii and befriended many people while taking portraits. In the end he did not make good on delivering photographs that were already paid for, and left town with Georgia Bennett's work including the headdress, an apron and leggings. It took over a year for the thief to be arrested and imprisoned, and Georgia's weavings returned. This was her response."
    - 6a. Tluu Xaada Naay (Canoe Peoples House) Dancers, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 7. Cynthia Samuels (Haida name Gulee), 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 8. Bryce Williams, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 9. Roberta Kennedy (Haida name Kung Jaadee), 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 10. Tiffany Vanderhoop, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 11. Then and Now, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Coronation
    - 12. Allen Davidson is crowned with Hereditary Chief's headdress of white ermine and frontlet of red cedar and abalone., 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 13. Wrapped in Ravens Tail Blanket, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 14. Chief leads men in first dance, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 15. Haida women's dance, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 16. It is always about the generations..., 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 17)
      "It is always about the generations and encouraging children from a very young age in the ways of the Haida culture."
    - 17. Two worlds, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 18. Dancers from Skidegate honor the new chief, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 19. Skidegate Moon Dance, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 20. Hereditary Chief Roy Collison, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 21. Eagle Dancer of tomorrow, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Kwakwak'awakw
    Alert Bay, Cormorant Island, British Columbia, Canada
    "My photographs are set in the complicated context of the raw emotional, and spiritual energy of the Potlatch rather than the cloistered museum setting, or posed studio images. Here in the atmosphere of pageantry where dancers, and singers adorned in the living art of woven wool Chilkat robes, cedar hats, and button blankets regalia, magnificent sculpted masks engage, storytelling dances, songs, and recitations that reaffirm families spiritual status inherited from transcendent, primordial ancestors with the intangible treasures of honor and power. Keeping the moments of the past, the present, and the future as one fluid continuum."
    - 22. This Mortuary Pole was raised in 2009, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 23)
      "[In 2009] Kwakwaka'wakw hereditary leader and artist Beau Dick called a Potlatch and invited the Haida to Potlatch in memory of their shared history.
      [According to Candace Weir White,] 'There was no formal, 'golden-western-civilized way-invitation' for this event, it wasn't put out like that. It was oral. This is how our people used to do things - the word was spread up and down the coast and the message would get around. People would either go or not, and we went - we took the invitation seriously.... We'd heard about the trip and we knew its significance, we were going!'
      Small Pox wiped out as much as sixty percent of the Haida population. In many villages one hundred percent were lost. There are stories from White and Native People as to how this all was handled. Claims that a Minister instructed the Haida that God was punishing them for their mortuary practices and Totemic Art, and would only give vaccines to those who would convert, while others regaled the Hudson Bay Company for providing vaccines for Haida in Victoria. That is until they began forcing Haida to leave when they fell ill to the disease brought on the Steamer Brother John from San Francisco, on March 12, 1862."
    - 23. Here at the base of the 178 feet tallest totem pole in the world we can see the Big House, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - 24. Protestation scrawled on the walls of the derelict St. Michael's Anglican Residential School, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 25)
      [Luck cites the following quote from the Anglican Church of Canada website about St. Michael's School at Alert Bay, British Columbia]: "'In 1877, the Church Missionary Society persuaded [Reverend] James Hall to relocate his Anglican mission at Fort Rupert, BC to nearby Alert Bay. The following year, [Reverend] Hall built a mission house where day schooling was first provided for native children, mostly drawn from the local reserve-ancestors of today's Nimpkish Band. It would soon be expanded into a full residential school. The mission was located on Cormorant Island, off the northeast shore of Vancouver Island. The adjacent village of Alert Bay soon became a thriving commercial fishing centre, the livelihood for native and non-native alike."
    - 25. Protestation scrawled on the walls of the derelict St. Michael's Anglican Residential School, 2012 Summer (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - 26. Gathering for the unveiling of a Totem Pole dedicated to the Kwakwaka'wakw people [probably] in recognition of the chief, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - 27. Kwakwaka'wakw Chiefs, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - 28. The Big House awaits, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 29)
      "The Alert Bay Big House is modeled on the traditional residences of the Kwakwaka'wakw, where extended families, numbering as many as fifty people. Completed May 1966 this building is primarily used for potlatches. The Big House was enlarged and repainted c. 1987, at which time 'Namgis artist, Doug Cranmer, designed the extended house front. The Big House was lost to fire on August 29, 1997.
      The Grand opening of the new Big House that we see now was held May 29-30, 1999."
    - 29. Hereditary leader and artist Beau Dick instructs the Women's Dance to begin, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - 30. The Women's Dance begins the ceremonies, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - 31. Beau Dick leads an adoption dance, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - 32. Haida Dancers enter the Big House, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - 33. Artist Corey Bullpit and Gwaliga Hart wearing Bear Mask, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - 34. Christian White sings after presenting Beau Dick with a copper shield, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - 35. Beau Dick begins his dance with the copper shield in appreciation of receiving the gift, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 36)
      "Coppers are a sign of wealth and status, and bragging rights Beau reminded me."
    - 36. The Hereditary Chiefs stand in recognition of Christian White's gift of a copper shield to Beau Dick, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 37)
      "An aside, I was allowed to participate in the creation of this Copper. I was honored by the experience."
    - 37. With this revealing of new masks carved and painted for the Potlatch the ceremonies enter a new phase of the celebrations and rituals, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Hamatsa
    "Vital to Kwakwaka'wakw culture, and Beau's Potlatch is the highly ritualistic, secret society of the Hamatsa. This arcane sequence of dances serves to initiate new members to the Hamatsa Secret Society."
    - 38. First in the Hamatsa ceremonies the initiate remains possessed by Baxwbakwalanuksiwe' ("Man-Eater from the north")..., 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 39)
      ".. ., must be lured out of the woods and brought into the Big House to be tamed, as his symbolically enacts his cannibalistic possession."
    - 39. The initiate enacts his Gwaxwgwakwalanuksiwe', the man-eating raven, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 40)
      ".. ., the most prestigious role in the Supernatural Man-Eater Birds community."
    - 40. Galuxwadzuwus ("Crooked-Beak of Heaven"), 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 41)
      "This part of the ritual was in a distant dark area of the Big House; Consequently I was unable to capture the event. Huxhukw (supernatural Crane-Like Bird who cracks skulls of men to suck out their brains)."
    - 41. As his evolution continues the initiate is offered the copper shield that will commemorate his accomplishment, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - 42. New ceremonies may now begin, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - 43. The fire is an important part of the ceremonies as dancers glide over the dirt floor introducing a series of gift givings, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - 44. Here Hereditary Namgis Chief Bill Cranmer displays a mask carved for him by Beau Dick..., 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 45)
      "... in recognition and appreciation for his hard work in bringing around the Potlatch."
    - 45. Here Hereditary Chief shows off his bent wood box, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - 46. The young man squatting on the right, beside his father holding his copper shield, witnessed by Hereditary Kwakwak'awakw matriarch in wheelchair..., 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 47)
      ".. ., has been initiated into the Cannibal Society and is prepared to be Hereditary Chief."
    - 47. Here father standing holding rattle and Copper Shield, son kneeling, and Beau Dick's family attest to the accomplishment, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 48)
      "These two photographs will be collected by Beau Dick and held in the Umista Museum to stand against any claims."
    - 48. Masked dancer of the woodland spirits, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - 49. Masked dancer, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - 50. Masked dancer of the spirit world, 2012 Summer (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - 51. Masked dancers, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - 52. Spirit world mask dancer, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - 53. Masked dancer "Wind", 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - 54. Masked dancer, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - 55. Sun Dancer and Beau [Dick], 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - 56. Spirit World mask, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - 57. Beau Dick dances in contemplation around a fire that is encircled with the mask of the spirit world, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - 58. Beau Dick directs the beginning of the mask burning ceremony, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 59)
      "The late day sun shafting cold light into the Big House.
      The mask-burning portion of the Potlatch remains highly controversial. Hereditary Chief Beau Dick has done this once before to the consternation of many and the support of many more.
      It is Chief Dick's belief that the masks have been used enough, and that it is time to free the spirits to the spirit world."
    - 59. The fire of masks, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - 60. The sun mask, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - 61. Beaver Spirit mask, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - 62. Spirit mask, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - 63. Raven Transformation mask, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - 64. Raven transforms into man, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - 65. Halibut mask dancer, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - 66. Spirit World masks, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - 67. Killer Whale mask dancers, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - 68. Sea lion mask, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - 69. Thunder Bird head detail, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - 70. Thunder Bird takes flight, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - 71. Thunder Bird takes flight, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - 72. Puk mask, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - 73. Octopus mask, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - 74. Sun mask, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 75)